Who doesn't just speak about businesses?
He redefines how leaders think about growth, scale
and execution.
Across continents and across boardrooms, across industries, he
has consistently challenged one thing, can your idea
survive reality?
Vusi Tembekwayo is a globally acclaimed entrepreneur, venture
capitalist, author and one of Africa's most influential
business thinkers.
Widely known for transforming how leaders approach growth
and execution, he's the founder and CEO of
My Growth Fund Venture Partners, where he supports
high-growth African businesses with capital, strategy and
scale frameworks.
He's also the founder of the School of
Scale, equipping entrepreneurs with the discipline required to
build sustainable enterprises beyond ideas.
Vusi has advised governments, multinational corporations and founders
across continents, consistently challenging them to move beyond
inspiration into structure, systems and measurable results.
He represents execution at his highest level, where
ideas are tested, stretched and proven through scale.
Ladies and gentlemen, get ready for clarity, structure
and truth.
Please put your hands together and give a
warm platform welcome to Vusi Tembekwayo.
Thank you so much, thank you.
Thank you ma'am, you're too kind.
What a day, good afternoon everybody.
Hey Charlie, we are here, hello family.
All right, let's get started.
I'd like everybody to take a seat if
you don't mind.
I have five ideas that I flew 11
hours and prepared 50 slides to come and
share with you and I have to do
all of that in exactly the next 30
minutes.
So with your permission, I know I'm good,
you know I'm good, we all know we're
good.
We're gonna get right to the meat of
what we're sharing today.
Is that fair?
Excellent.
I need my clicker, Emmanuel, to get my
slides to move.
There's no clicker here, there's microphones, which I'm
happy to speak into, but it'd be great
for me to get the clicker.
So before we get started, can I just
say this morning my experience in traffic was
much better, much, much better than last time.
I'm not sure if it's something the government
has done or if it's because they removed
the fuel levy, but whatever it is, it's
workers day indeed.
Secondly, can we acknowledge my brother Pastor Portia
for putting this together?
Come on, yeah.
He's a gentleman and a scholar, he really
is and I love the stuff that his
media team has been doing, by the way,
online.
It looks absolutely great and I know he's
not here so I know you're gonna tell
him for us.
Let's give him another round of applause.
Excellent.
The third thing I wanted to say before
we get started, and please, the chaps at
the back, you're not allowed to run my
time yet because I'm still waiting for my
clicker.
So as soon as my clicker comes, then
you can time me down.
I'm already timing myself.
Thank you so much, ma'am.
Can we give her a round of applause?
Great work.
The third thing I wanted to say is
this.
You should have the privilege of being offended
in life.
Offence is good because offence means one of
two things.
One, that you care enough about whatever is
being said, or two, that what you have
believed has been so wrong that you're being
challenged.
So I gave myself one very simple mandate
coming here for my third platform, to offend
you.
That's all I came here to do and
I hope that in our time together, you're
gonna be offended.
Chaps, if you can put up my slides,
please, that'll be great.
Let's get started.
So I hope that in our time together,
I'm gonna share with you some ideas, share
with you some principles, share with you some
thinking that should offend you.
You should have the privilege of being offended.
Offence is fantastic.
So on screen, typically what they do, my
team forces me to do this, like, introduce
yourself.
I'm like, people know who I am.
I know who I am.
But I have, by God's grace, the privilege
of being the founder, no longer the CEO,
but I'm the founder and chairman of our
school of scale.
This is our Accelerator programme that we first
started when we were actually forming our venture
capital firm, circa 2016.
We celebrate 10 years this year in our
VC firm, My Growth Fund.
Thank you, to God be the glory, truly.
But we started first as My Growth Fund
Accelerate, because we were helping entrepreneurs that we
had invested in, because here was the problem
I realised, Pastor Poggio.
The problem was this.
We were taking this money and investing it
in these businesses, and for our first fund,
we couldn't get institutional backing.
And so I was lucky that I'd exited
a business, so I took my own money,
and I thought, well, if they won't give
me the money, I'll put my own money
down, and I'll prove the thesis.
And here's what I found.
I found that there was a correlation, not
necessarily a causation, but there was a correlation
between entrepreneurs, their race background, and their propensity
for success, that if they were young, black,
female, and from a poor background, or from
a village, they were most likely to fail.
And then I realised that all of the
white male entrepreneurs that we were helping, investing
in, or scaling businesses, were celestial beings.
Nowhere in the Bible did it say that
on the eighth day, God invented them.
They were just like you and me.
So the question I wanted to understand was
this.
What is it they knew that we didn't
that allowed them to succeed?
First, I was offended, then I spurred into
action.
And over the past 10 years, we have
refined our work, refined our thesis, we have
tested it so well that today the School
of Scale is in South Africa, we're in
Ghana, we're in Kenya, we're in Zambia, we
just opened an office in Jamaica because we've
signed a massive deal in the Caribbean Islands,
and our head office is in Delaware.
So I can speak about the work we
do with some semblance of certainty.
We know what works.
I'm going to share with you a little
bit of that today.
I also have this podcast called Ideas That
Matter.
There we are, there we are.
Last year we won Apple's, we're on the
top four globally under the Apple category for
business podcasts, the only African podcast to feature
in that series.
And here's why that's important for me, and
I'll make the point very quickly.
If you look at the world and you
look at popular culture, you realise that Africans
are over-represented.
And I'm going to share with you a
little bit about what I mean in a
moment, but just look at our conventional history.
We look at music, Africans.
You look at theatre, Africans.
You look at Hollywood, Bollywood, Nollywood, Africans.
You find us everywhere.
The only place you find the Africa story
absent is business.
You look at our politics, Africans.
Liberation movements, Africans.
But the minute you talk business, commerce, P
&L, balance sheets, suddenly the African voices are
few and far between.
And here is the problem.
Every single one of our ambitions is not
possible unless we control resources.
And secondly, we come from the world's most
resource-rich part of the world.
How can we have the resources but be
poor?
Something is broken here, comrades.
Anyway, I also chair Watermark Africa Fund.
That's our private equity firm, now year six,
based out of the DIFC in Dubai.
And most recently, I've been raising a fund
called 154.
I'm very proud of the name, by the
way.
154.
One continent, 54 countries.
It's a Pan-African fund that targets family
businesses, and effectively what we're doing with our
thesis is we're looking for family businesses that
are in generational transition.
There is something fascinating happening in the world
at the moment, and it's even more acute
here in Africa.
Generational business owners, family businesses.
The person who founded that business is no
longer old enough to run the business, but
typically what's happening is their children don't want
to run their business.
They've all become chartered accountants and lawyers.
They've gone on to work in other parts
of the world, and yet they've built these
businesses that are the bedrock of many of
their economies.
And so we're just about to hit first
close in that business, and I'm very, very
excited.
And then apart from that, I write some
books, nothing major to mention.
They're sold over 1 million copies.
Just, you know, God is good.
God is good.
All right, let's get started.
Just to make sure that we're all on
the same page, and to prove to you
that I'm not an AI, and knowing how
long you've all been sat down, I'm going
to play a little game with you.
I'm going to give you some emojis.
The emojis are going to be a brand,
and if you know the brand, just shout
it out.
Here is the first one.
What brand is this?
Emmanuel, can I get my coffee?
No, it's not for September guy.
Think about what this symbolises.
Netflix.
Come on, use your third brain.
Here's this.
What about this one?
What brand is this?
Thanks, Manny.
Blackberry.
It's trailing.
Oh, I see.
You guys are trailing.
I see.
Are we all on the same page, guys?
This screen and that screen are showing different
things, eh?
Red Bull.
All right, now here's what it is that
I want to speak to you about today.
If you have a pen and paper, I
want you to write down these two words.
These are the two words that I'm going
to speak to you about today.
Put it back on screen, guys.
Don't take it off, please.
Very important.
I need it back on screen consistently.
I see you're having a problem with the
run.
Let me go back.
There we go.
These are the two words, guys.
Founder's mindset.
This is what I came to talk to
you about today.
My thesis, which I hope offends you, is
that not every single business owner is a
founder.
Not every single entrepreneur is a founder.
Not every single leader is a founder.
There are a set of things that make
founders different.
The most important of these things is that
founders know that they will come a time
when the thing they have founded has outgrown
them.
In fact, they build it intentionally so that
the thing they have founded outgrows them.
And so my challenge for us here today
is going to be sharing with you what
is in the mindset of what it takes
to be founders and how founders build and
scale their businesses.
Manny, can I get like a tissue or
something to wipe while I'm up here?
That'll be great.
Thank you so much.
The greatest poet of the 20th century, a
man whose contribution to poetry outpaces William Shakespeare
and T.S. Eliot.
A man whose contribution to poetry outpaces many
of our best poets, including Rumi, by the
way, is the man who, in my opinion,
is the greatest poet of the 20th century.
His name is Jay-Z.
That was a joke.
But Jay-Z says men lie, women lie,
numbers don't.
I'm a numbers guy.
I live in the world of numbers.
I spent most of last night running a
Monte Carlo simulation on our recent capital race.
So I'm gonna share with you some numbers
here today.
Now, for any of you who ever find
yourself raising capital, I'm gonna give you a
little tip here.
Don't forget, there's one of two things you
need to do when you show numbers.
First, if it's on a graph, it must
be true.
So always present your data on a graph.
Secondly, if it's a statistic, always share it
within two decimal places, because 69.98%
just sounds a lot more certain than 70%.
I'm giving you tips here.
Write this down, right?
They're not paying attention, you know.
Right.
Some work done by PitchBook, and they're a
publication that talks about the world of capital
markets, venture capital, small businesses.
They did some work to look at the
number of deals that have been done where
companies that were founder-led were bought.
This is the graph of what that looks
like.
It starts in the year I was born,
the year of our Lord, 1985, and goes
up until May 1924.
I'm gonna break it down for you, don't
worry about it, just let me help you
understand it quite quickly.
This is the number of actual mergers and
acquisition transactions done every single year for all
of these years.
Said differently, there is more money looking to
back founders' businesses than there are founders building
businesses.
So if you're not attracting the capital, the
capital isn't the problem.
You are.
And a lot of what that you are
is, has something to do sometimes with the
business you're starting, often with the timing you're
raising money, but more important than not with
the geography of where you're actually based.
I'll show you what I mean in a
moment.
So again, I'm a numbers guy, I broke
these numbers up into the trend lines, and
I looked first at the first quartile period,
and then I looked finally at the last
quartile period, and what do you notice?
Between 1985 and circa 2000, by the year
2000, there were 40,000 deals.
40,000 deals where money was buying businesses
led by founders.
There was only 12 months in a year,
so that's about 3,800 businesses being bought
every month.
There's only four weeks in a month, that's
about a thousand businesses a week.
There's only five working days a week, that's
200 businesses every single day, somebody transacting and
buying a business that somebody has built.
And by the way, none of these people
are angels, they are just human beings, they're
just like you and me, and they just
figured out a way.
Net number had grown by the year, by
the time we got to the year 2020,
it was around 60,000.
These numbers are, and it's going to increase.
I'm not sure if you're aware of this,
so I'll share it with you very, very
quickly.
There is a statistic that says, over the
past five years, the United States has printed,
listen to this, the United States over the
past five years has printed 50% of
US dollar currency that it has printed since
the existence of the United States.
The comrades are not following me.
The United States was founded, you could argue
the time, but it was founded circa 1776
at the Gettysburg Address.
Abraham Lincoln, four score and seven years ago,
our forefathers set foot on this continent and
brought forth a new nation.
That was 1776.
And between 1776 and five years ago, all
of the money that they printed, for all
of the problems that they printed, all of
the USD that ever went into the global
economic system, not only physical money, but digital
money that goes into your computers as well,
until five years ago, they have now printed
half of that over the last five years.
There is more money today than there are
good ideas and good founders, and I am
absolutely certain of it.
The question is, how do we unlock it?
And that's what it is that I came
here to share.
Well, first we need to start with where
we are.
Let's look at your own economy here.
What are you guys, $340 billion economy, give
or take?
It depends on what's happening with the Naira.
I can't laugh, but I laugh.
So think about four key markets that you
could build in, right?
So first yours, second your neighbour, who by
the way, I was there a week ago,
they said I should tell you that they
have better jollof than you do.
Not my words, Charlie, but there are 115,
120 billion dollar economy, give or take.
And then of course, Kenya, where I was
transiting through three days ago, we have a
business in Kenya, there are 140 billion dollar
economy, and then of course, the greatest country
in the continent of Africa, my home, South
Africa.
Now the largest economy in Africa, I need
to tell you, we are once again the
giants of Africa.
I just want to remind you that there
are two countries in Africa, it's South Africa
and everybody else.
Don't worry, that's the rich man's laugh.
When you're rich, you laugh like that.
See, when you're poor, you laugh like you're
fighting.
I'm not fighting anybody.
These markets alone present a one trillion dollar
economic opportunity.
So more money being printed in the world
than has ever been the case, more money
making rounds than has ever been the case,
and that money must be invested somewhere, it's
looking for founders to build businesses.
Then we are in an environment that presents
at the very least a trillion dollar economic
opportunity, but what you must understand is that
legacies are not hoped for, they're built.
So the question is, how do you build
a legacy?
The first thing you must do is you
must understand your context.
The context in which you're operating, ladies and
gentlemen, is everything.
Context in which you're operating.
I'm going to quickly, very quickly, quickly share
with you the context of Africa.
First, sub-Saharan Africa, which we are in,
presents the largest economic growth opportunity of any
other region in the world.
Of any other region in the world.
And that, by the way, includes the United
States, it includes advanced economies.
We present a 4.6 percent economic growth
opportunity on aggregate, just in this region of
ours that we call sub-Saharan Africa.
Second, we are the world's engine for growth.
Why?
Because we have the world's youngest population.
We have the world's youngest population.
For what it's worth, Europe is old and
getting older.
Why do you think they are so keen
to take young Africans who are qualified?
You think they're doing it out of the
goodness of their heart?
These visas they make available for us?
Suddenly, when we qualify as engineers and software
engineers and doctors and lawyers, they're doing it
because that's what drives economic growth.
They need us there.
I can assure you, need us far more
than we need them.
Europe is old and getting older.
The Americas are kind of stagnant.
Asia is slightly younger, set aside Japan, which
has a number of structural problems.
But if you look at the Africa story,
just look at those numbers, guys.
Over 50% of the population of Africa
is under the age of 50.
In your country, Nigeria, over 50% of
the population here is under the age of
18.
Do you know what that means?
That means there are over 100 million people
who are not yet economically active.
So if I was building a business, where
would I build it?
In Luxembourg or Liechtenstein, where the population is
less than 10 million?
Or would I build it in a place
where the population of people who are not
yet economically active is over 100 million alone?
The problem with us is we don't know
how to execute on this opportunity.
The data is there.
How do you execute on it?
Second point I want to make, standards of
living are improving.
Most of us here, I imagine, didn't grow
up in urban areas, but you live in
one now because we're all urbanising.
We're all moving to the urban centres.
Our standards of living are improving.
Our connectivity is improving.
Suddenly we have the internet.
We can download things and internet speeds are
getting faster.
I see you guys let that South African
guy called Elon Musk come and launch Starlink
here.
You should have listened to South Africa because
I want to believe that he's done something
like triple the prices over the past few
months that he's been here.
Good luck.
You're going, you're going, hey, you don't know
what you've done to yourselves.
Us as South Africans, we shall watch you
suffer well.
Third, where will this engine for growth come
from?
So I'm going to give you two comparative
analyses.
The first I'm going to do is show
you the world's largest companies 10 years ago
and circa now, and then I'm going to
ask you what does this look like in
Africa?
These are the world's largest companies in 2011.
What do you notice?
Of the top 10 largest companies in 2011,
only two are not, only, yeah, only three
are technology firms.
The other seven are not technology firms.
Now fast-forward 10 years and suddenly 10
years later, only two are not technology firms.
This was 2021.
This is pre the IPO of SpaceX, which
is about to take place.
It'll be the largest IPO in the history
of IPOs.
Until recently, that record has been held by
Saudi Aramco.
A lot of people don't know what the
Aramco in Saudi Aramco stands for.
It's the Arab American company because it was
the Americans that helped the Saudi Arabians actually
create much of what is today their oil
industry.
Their relationship goes back many, many decades.
This is the world, fast-moving and moving
into the technology space.
Now look at us.
Come to Africa.
These are Africa's largest companies, of course dominated
by South Africa, of course dominated by South
Africa.
Just sitting with you that you guys don't
feature there.
No, I joke, I joke, I joke.
But what do you notice?
About three of those are technology businesses.
Much of them are actually agricultural and mining
businesses because the truth is Africa is still
a economy of holes.
That's what Africans are really good at.
We're very good at holes.
We're good at digging them and pulling things
out of them, mining or digging them and
planting things into them, agriculture.
It isn't to say we shouldn't use the
technology advantage but it is to say we
need to play for the game we have
been gifted.
So I came to ask a question, who
here is going to build the business for
the future?
So that was the first point I want
to make.
Second point I want to make.
Capital follows scale.
Tosin was talking earlier about his journey at
MoneyPoint and what did you notice when he
first opened his presentation?
He shared with you guys the macro data
of how big their business is.
He wasn't sharing that with you to impress
you, he was sharing it with you to
let you know capital follows scale.
He's been able to attract the capital he's
been able to attract because he's been able
to build a business that scaled as fast
as his business is scaled.
I should say it's something that I'm constantly
moaning about to my own peers in South
Africa about.
The rate at which yourselves here have been
able to scale technology businesses is just mind
-blowing, absolutely mind-blowing.
But capital follows scale and if capital does
follow scale then what are the four things
you need to scale?
This is what the data tells us.
The first reason most entrepreneurs in Africa don't
scale is because they don't know how to
synthesise their operations.
Tosin was talking about it, he spoke about
standard operating processes and procedures.
He spoke about running a rules-based environment
rather than a people-based environment.
In our environment we call it synthesising the
operation so that even if you are not
at work, work continues.
The second is most African entrepreneurs don't know
how to implement growth drivers.
Every single business has three things that if
you did the business grows.
Everything else is traffic and so what most
African entrepreneurs do is you're managing noise.
The role of a leader is to remove
the noise and focus on the signal.
So let me ask you here today, those
of you running a business, what are the
three things that if you did today your
turnover would double?
Do those things.
Everything else is noise and if you don't
know what those three things are, your homework
when you leave here is go and find
out what are the three things I should
be doing.
Third, build based on insights.
This is probably the one I feel most
passionately about.
When you first start a business you succeed
because of instinct but to scale a business
you'll succeed because of insight.
You start a business because you feel it
in your stomach.
You can get a sense that something's going
to move.
Someone says to you this is what we
need and so you start trying something, testing
something, going to market with something and go
wow this actually works.
That's instinct.
But what you've got to figure out are
what are the tools and technologies I need
to put in place to move from instinct
to insight.
Instinct is what I feel, insight is what
I know.
And so too many of us are still
ten years or five years into a business
and you're still running it by how I
feel.
And then the last, when you're managing people
if you do not have the ability to
align incentives you will fail.
Your people must have incentives that are directly
aligned with the business objectives you want to
drive.
Tosin called it structure.
It's exactly the same idea.
I'll prove it to you.
This deck that I'm sharing with you, this
is my fourth keynote this week.
Next year I've got, next week I've got
six keynotes in three continents in six different
countries.
No, no, don't clap.
Let me make the point I want to
make.
I didn't see this keynote until last night.
I didn't see it.
I didn't need to see it.
I have a team of people around me
whose incentives are aligned with mine.
In fact my brother when I was supposed
to be on a meeting with you on
the call, the briefing meeting, because this is
how my process works, when a client invites
me to come and speak we jump on
a call, we get a briefing.
The first time I think you were busy
and had something going.
The second time I was flying somewhere so
I couldn't jump on the call with Pastor
Pardew, but I had four people in my
team who jumped on my call.
My head of operations, my head of protocol,
my head of marketing, and my executive assistant.
All of them jumped on the call.
They listened, the call was recorded, it went
to an AI system that we run that
told us of all of the ideas and
things I speak about.
What are the three simple ideas I could
speak about to synthesise it?
Then it went to my design team, which
is headed by a young lady who sits
in South Africa but is aided by other
people who sit in India, Pakistan, and Sri
Lanka.
They designed the whole presentation, sent it, my
quality control went through the whole process, headed
by my marketing team.
Two nights ago she sent it to me.
Last night when I landed I checked it.
Synthesised operations.
Now everything I'm sharing with you is not
rocket science.
It's just put the system in place so
that regardless of where you're expected to deliver
the outcomes, it makes no difference the same.
But you have to align incentives.
So what does aligning incentives look like?
Well I'll share it with you.
When I leave here, the good people here
at Covenant Nation will get an email from
my team.
That email has a link.
It'll direct them to a scoring sheet where
they get to score me and how I've
performed.
And in that scoring sheet they score my
performance, be nice, they'll score my keynote, but
they will also score my presentation, my ideas,
and the design.
So when we come together at the end
of a quarter and we're dispersing quarterly bonuses,
it's not just based on who performed well
based on their own feelings, but actually based
on what clients have said.
That way my team has to do the
right job because they get paid to do
the right job.
Simply aligning incentives.
So you're running a business, a retail business,
and while you're here, you've got somebody in
your shops helping customers.
How do you know that they're helping customers?
We have a young man in our business
who runs a business called Monbiu Afrique.
He's a young Zimbabwean man, a young man
from Zimbabwe who grew up in Zim, then
moved to South Africa, started this business called
Monbiu Afrique.
And they sell apparel, but they also sell
ouds.
They sell those very deep, rich kind of
perfumes that come from the Arabias.
Two years ago I said to him, the
market here is too small, you need to
move.
He moved.
He now has a store in Beverly Hills
in Los Angeles.
But I know anytime I walk past any
of Chase's store, I know that if any
of his salespeople see me, the first thing
they're gonna say is, sir I have a
smell from Cape Town, would you like to
smell it?
That's a sales script.